[
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 1,
        "year": 2009,
        "question": "<p>(a) What is legitimacy in government?</p><p>(b) Outline any five ways of acquiring legitimacy. </p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong>(a) </strong>Legitimacy is the recognition and acceptance of the rulers by the people as expressed in compliance to the authority.</p><p><strong>(b)</strong>(i) Acceptable ideology of the government i.e. socialist, capitalist, etc.</p><p>(ii) Charisma of the leaders: This could be based on their honesty of purpose, uprightness or oratory.</p><p>(iii) Method of changing government e.g. Through free and fair elections.</p><p>(iv) Performance of the government i.e. if the government engages in appealing projects.</p><p>(v) Popular/mass political participation and support.</p><p>(vi) Open door administration and opportunities for debates and criticisms.</p><p>(vii) Acceptance by the international community.</p><p>(viii) Type of foreign policy/diplomacy pursued.</p><p>(ix) Observance of the Rule of Law</p><p>(x) Respect for customs and traditions. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 2,
        "year": 2009,
        "question": "<p>Outline six disadvantages of an unwritten constitution</p>",
        "answer": "<p><em><strong>Disadvantages of an unwritten constitution are:                                                                                                                                             </strong></em>              (i)It can be manipulated by political leaders.</p><p>(ii) It may lead to emergence of dictatorship.</p><p>(iii) It deprives citizens from knowing their rights and duties.</p><p>(iv) Lack of codification of 10 fundamental rights of citizens undermines the ability to seek redress when rights are violated.</p><p>(v) It creates ambiguities which can lead to general misinterpretations.</p><p>(vi) It is not suitable for multi-ethnic/multi racial societies.</p><p>(vii) It does not make for easy reference/study.</p><p>(viii) Not easy to ascertain unconstitutional acts.</p><p>(ix) Possible emergence of conflicts among the organs of government due to none definition of their roles and powers.<br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 3,
        "year": 2009,
        "question": "<p>Highlight the main functions of the executive in a modern state.</p>",
        "answer": "<p><em><strong>Main functions of the executive in a modern state are:  </strong></em>                                                                                                                                                (i)Policy formulation is one of the major functions of the executive.</p><p>(ii) Implements the laws made in the state.</p><p>(iii) Appointment and removal of top officials of the state.</p><p>(iv) Declaration of war.</p><p>(v) He conducts foreign policy of the state</p><p>(vi) He exercises the prerogative of mercy.</p><p>(vii) The executive initiates bills, defends them and recommends measures for laws to be made.</p><p>(viii) He prepares and delivers the annual income and expenditure of the state.</p><p>(ix) Maintenance of law and order through the police and other law enforcement agencies.</p><p>(x) Signing of bills into laws.</p><p>(xi) The executive can make laws through delegated authority.</p><p>(xii) Provision of social amenities and infrastructural/facilities, e.g. roads.</p><p>(xiii) The executive can declare a state of emergency.</p><p>(xiv) He performs ceremonial functions. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 4,
        "year": 2009,
        "question": "<p>(a) Explain concurrent functions in a federation.</p><p>(b) Outline five features of a confederal system of government.</p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong><em>Functions of concurrent in a federation.                                                                                                     </em></strong>                                                                    <strong>(a)</strong>Concurrent functions are the list of functions in a federal constitution whereby both federating units and central government can legislate and execute independently.</p><p><strong><em>(b) Five features of a confederal system of government: </em></strong>                                                                                                                                             (i) It has a very weak center.</p><p>(ii) The confederating units are nearly autonomous.</p><p>(iii) Secession of any component unit is allowed.</p><p>(iv) It allows component units to develop at their own pace</p><p>(v) Citizens' allegiance is more to the component units than to the confederacy.</p><p>(vi) Individual units co-operate on specific areas such as foreign affairs, currency, defence, etc.</p><p>(vii) The confederal constitution is flexible.</p><p>(viii) A confederal state is politically unstable.</p><p>(ix) Each confederating unit has its own armed forces and police.</p><p>(x) The 12 confederal state depends on subventions from the units. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 5,
        "year": 2009,
        "question": "<p>(a) What is a manifesto?</p><p>(b) Outline five factors that determine the electoral success of a political party.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(a) A manifesto is a document that outlines the electoral promises or programmes of a political party which it intends to fulfill when elected into office.</p><p><em><strong>(b) Five factors that determine the electoral success of a political party: </strong></em>                                                                                                                   (i) Broad-based membership.</p><p>(ii) Financial capacity of the party.</p><p>(iii) Massive sensitization and education of the electorate by the party.</p><p>(iv) Very strong party discipline.</p><p>(v) Well-organized party structures.</p><p>(vi) Well establishec and organized auxiliary bodies within the party such as the Youth and Women's wings, etc.</p><p>(vii) Effective propa-ganda machinery e.g. the press.</p><p>(viii) Effective and goal-directed leadership.</p><p>(ix) Good party programmes or manifesto.</p><p>(x) Impressive past performance.</p><p>(xi) Transparent electoral process.</p><p>(xii) The caliber and reputation of a party's candidates.<br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 6,
        "year": 2009,
        "question": "<p>Identify any six functions of the Oyomesi in the pre-colonial Oyo empire.</p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong><em>Six functions of the Oyomesi in the pre-colonial Oyo empire: </em></strong>                                                                                                                                 (i)They took part in the selection of a ne% Alaafin.</p><p>(ii) They initiated laws.</p><p>(iii) They acted as checks on the powers of Oba e.g. removal of Alaafin from office.</p><p>(iv) They ensured implementation of policies.</p><p>(v)They performed religious functions.</p><p>(vi) They performed judicial functions.</p><p>(vii) They assisted in the organization of youths for communal development.</p><p>(viii) They advised the Alaafin on good governance.</p><p>(ix) They helped in the maintenance of law and order.</p><p>(x) They took part in the 3 installation of a new Alaafin.<br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 7,
        "year": 2009,
        "question": "<p>Highlight four reasons for the European colonization of West Africa.</p>",
        "answer": "<p><em><strong>Four reasons for the European Colonisation of West Africa:                                                                                                                                        </strong></em>(i)They were in search of new markets fcr legitimate trade.</p><p>(ii) Extension of cultural heritage  e.g. The French wanted to extend their self acclaimed agriculture to Africa hence their policy of assimilation.</p><p>(iii) To provide security for their traders, trade routes and workers</p><p>(iv) To halt slave trade and slavery.</p><p>(v) To find outlets for surplus capital.</p><p>(vi) Search for raw materials for home industries.</p><p>(vii) To acquire more colonies for their glory and prestige</p><p>(viii) To find employment for displaced Europeans <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 8,
        "year": 2009,
        "question": "<p>Identify four weaknesses of the British Colonial administration in West Africa.</p>",
        "answer": "<p><em><strong>Four weaknesses of the British colonial administration in West Africa:</strong></em>                                                                                                                      (i)The legislative councils were dominated by British officials.</p><p>(ii) The elective principle was restricted i.e. limited franchise.</p><p>(iii) Sidelined the educated elite and limited their representation in the colonial administration.</p><p>(iv) The executive councils we dominated by British officials</p><p>(v) The governors had double votes which could be used to promote British colonial policies as against African interests.</p><p>(vi) Governors were dictators as they had the power to accept or reject advice given by the executive councils and laws passed by the legislative councils.</p><p>(vii) The British dominant interest in Banking, Commerce, Mining were detrimental to the African interest.</p><p>(viii) British administration in some cases interfered with the people's culture and trading e.g. warrant chiefs and disposition of traditional rulers.</p><p>(ix) Electioneering democracy was limited to few areas of the colonies.</p><p>(x) The colonialists created artificial boundaries for their selfish interests.</p><p>(xi) The divide and rule policy created an uneven development. </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 9,
        "year": 2009,
        "question": "<p>Highlight four objectives of Nigeria Youth Movement.</p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong>Four objectives of the Nigerian Youth Movement:</strong>                                                                                                                                                          (i) To develop a united nation out of the conglomeration of people who inhabited Nigeria.</p><p>(ii) To pressurize the government to award scholarship to the youths to study abroad.</p><p>(iii) To strive for the establishment of a new legislative council built on the principle of an unofficial majority.</p><p>(iv) To demand for equal economic opportunities for Nigerians with those enjoyed by foreigners.</p><p>(v) To demand better pay for Africans in the Civil Service.</p><p>(vi) To demand for higher executive appointments for Africans within the civil service.</p><p>(vii) To see that more use are being made of Africans in the administrative branch of the public service.</p><p>(viii) To cooperate with all bodies whose aims and aspirations are similar to its own.</p><p>(ix) To struggle for the complete control of the Township Councils by Nigerians.</p><p>(x) To work for political emancipation of Nigerians with the aim of achieving complete autonomy within the British Empire. </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 10,
        "year": 2009,
        "question": "<p>Give any six functions of the president under the 1963 Constitution of Nigeria </p>",
        "answer": "<p><em><strong>Six functions of the President under the 1963 constitution of Nigeria:</strong></em>                                                                                                                    (i)As Head of State, he performed ceremonial functions.</p><p>(ii) He appointed the leader of the party that won majority seats in Parliament at the general election as the Prime Minister.</p><p>(iii) With the advice of the Prime Minister, he dissolved the House of Representatives after a vote of no confidence had been passed.</p><p>(iv) He authorized any member of the Council of Ministers to perform the functions of the Prime Minister when the latter was absent or in-capacitated.</p><p>(v) He approved all the Prime Minister's appointments or nominees into political positions.</p><p>(vi) He assented or signed into law all bills passed by the parliament.</p><p>(vii) On the advice of the parliament, he could remove judges, directors of audit, etc, from office.</p><p>(viii) He approved treaties on behalf of the country.</p><p>(ix) He addressed the Parliament at the beginning and end of the legislative year.</p><p>(x) He declared a state of emergency or war.</p><p>(xi) He summoned, prorogued and dissolved parliament on the advice of the Prime Minister.</p><p>(xii) He appointed Parliamentary secretaries from among the Senators and Members of House of Representatives.</p><p>(xiii) He exercised prerogative of mercy.</p><p>(xiv)As commander-in-chief, he controlled the Armed Forces. </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 11,
        "year": 2009,
        "question": "<p>Explain six causes of the first military intervention in Nigerian politics.</p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong><em> Six causes of the first military intervention in Nigerian politics:</em></strong>                                                                                                                                  (i)The Western Regional electoral crisis of 1965.</p><p>(ii) The general electoral crises of 1964 between the Nigerian National Alliance (NNA) and United Progressive Grand Alliance (UPGA).</p><p>(iii) The inter-tribal politics among the three major tribes Hausa/Fulani, lgbo and Yoruba.</p><p>(iv) The census crisis of 1962/63.</p><p>(v) Inordinate ambition of the military to taste political power.</p><p>(vi) Corruption.</p><p>(vii) Inter and intra-party conflicts.</p><p>(viii) Politicization of the army e.g. involvement of the army in the Western Regional crisis and the Tiv riots in 1964.</p><p>(ix) Influence of other coups in Africa e.g. Egypt, Togo, Central African Republic, etc.</p><p>(x) Economic mismanagement by the politicians.</p><p>(xi) Nepotism/sectionalism in the public service. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 12,
        "year": 2009,
        "question": "<p>State six weaknesses of the United Nations Organization (UNO)</p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong><em>State six weaknesses of the United Nations Organisation (UNO):                                                                                                                           </em></strong>(i)The ideological differences affected harmony within the Organization.</p><p>(ii) Constant border clashes/disputes among member-nations e.g. India and Pakistan</p><p>(iii) Inability of the United Nations to generate sufficient funds for its operations.</p><p>(iv) Inability of the Organization to effectively address the issue of poverty among member-states.</p><p>(v) Inability of the United Nations to curtail the excesses of some member-states.</p><p>(vi) The veto-power of the five permanent members of the Security Council renders the Organization ineffective.</p><p>(vii) Inability to own a military High Command to prevent wars.</p><p>(viii) Over-reliance of the United Nations on the United States of America.</p><p>(ix) Inability to resolve conflicts among some member-nations e.g. Israel and Palestine.</p><p>(x) Inability to control nuclear proliferation. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    }
]